Thanks.
Terima kasih.
We'll be late.
- Kita bisa terlambat. - Apa?
-Come on. -What?
- Ayo.
Oh, okay.
Benar! Baiklah.
Should I hold that for you?
Mau kubantu pegang?
-Sure. -All right.
- Ya. - Baik.
Good job.
Bagus.
Sol-i, you're running for class president?
Shin Sol-i, kau ingin jadi ketua kelas?
But you always copy my homework, doze off in class,
Kau selalu menyontek PR-ku, sering tidur, menggambar,
or doodle when you're less tired--
atau mengerjakan hal lain di kelas…
-Catch! -I'm just saying.
- Tangkap! - Akan tetapi,
I'm not saying there's anything wrong with that.
bukan berarti kau tak mampu.
No one in our class is class president material.
Maksudku, tak ada yang bisa jadi ketua di kelas kita.
Woo Dae-sung barely comes to school
Woo Dae-sung sering absen,
and Cha Heon doesn't even know his classmates' names.
Cha Heon tak ingat semua nama teman sekelas.
But my Ha-young--
Sementara Ha-young…
Heon, are you busy?
Heon, apa kau sibuk?
I finished writing my election speech.
Aku menulis naskah pidato ketua kelas.
Can you proofread it?
Bisa bantu periksa?
Sure. I'll catch you later.
Baiklah. Sampai nanti.
Okay.
Ya.
Are you really going to back off?
Lihat itu. Kau tetap akan menyerah?
Will you let that happen?
Kau akan tinggal diam?
No, right?
Tidak, 'kan?
"Hello, I'm Shin Sol-i!"
"Selamat siang. Aku Shin Sol-i."
It's not like they don't know who I am.
Teman-teman sekelas sudah tahu aku Shin Sol-i.
Oh, my gosh!
Astaga!
Why are you so down today?
Kenapa hari ini kau tak bersemangat?
Where's your spirit, Brother? Your voice used to ring throughout the whole school.
Ke mana semangatmu yang selalu menggema di sekolah, Kawan?
Let me see.
Biar kulihat.
"I, Shin Sol-i, will devote myself
"Aku, Shin Sol-i, akan mengerahkan seluruh tenaga
and do everything I can for class 1-7!"
dan kesetiaan demi Kelas 1-7."
"I, Wang Se-hyeong,
"Aku, Wang Se-hyeong,
will devote all my energy to my classmates
akan mengerahkan seluruh tenaga
and do everything I can for class 1-7!"
dan kesetiaan demi Kelas 1-7!"
-Wang Se-hyeong!
- Wang Se-hyeong!
-Vote for number three, Wang Se-hyeong!
- Kandidat tiga, Wang Se-hyeong!
By the way, Se-hyeong, can I have one more bread?
Se-hyeong, apa aku boleh makan roti ini?
Don't tell me you copied Se-hyeong's speech.
Kau tak menyontek naskah Se-hyeong, 'kan?
Did you have the same tutor then?
Kalian ikut kelas pidato bersama?
I'm doomed for sure.
Matilah aku. Aku pasti gagal.
Rather than using such a cliché,
Jangan buat pidato klise begitu.
find what only you can offer.
Pikirkanlah apa kelebihanmu.
Maybe I should just withdraw.
Apa aku menyerah saja?
Don't worry.
Jangan cemas.
You too have something to offer, Brother.
Kau pasti punya kelebihan, Kawan.
Which is what?
Misalnya apa?
What? My sincerity?
Apa? "Ketulusan"?
You may be like a punching bag right now,
Kini kau mungkin hanya kambing hitam tak berarti,
but you're without doubt going to do your best.
tapi kau akan berusaha maksimal, 'kan?
Of course.
Iya.
That alone makes you deserving of the title class president.
Itu saja cukup untuk menjadi ketua kelas yang baik.
Is that a compliment?
Itu pujian atau hinaan?
My Brother.
Kawanku!
You have excellent listening comprehension skills.
Pendengaranmu luar biasa.
Hey, Dae-sung!
Hei, Woo Dae-sung!
Or maybe not.
Ternyata bukan!
Heon!
Heon!
-What? -Who are you going to vote for?
- Ada apa? - Kau akan pilih siapa?
No, don't tell me.
Tidak! Jangan dijawab.
It should be anonymous, so don't.
Ini pemilihan rahasia. Dilarang memberi tahu.
Okay?
Ya?
Anyway, I promise to do my best, so trust me on that.
Pokoknya, aku akan berusaha keras. Jadi, dukunglah aku.
ELECTION DAY
HARI PEMILIHAN KETUA KELAS
Ms. Moon and fellow students, hello.
Selamat siang, Ibu Guru dan hadirin sekalian.
I'm Shin Sol-i.
Aku Shin Sol-i.
I'm fully aware that my candidacy
Pasti banyak di antara kalian yang kaget
shocked many of you
atau tidak setuju
I don't get good grades,
Nilaiku tidak bagus,
nor am I a model student.
dan bukan murid teladan.
Also, I'm not a natural born leader or particularly humorous.
Kepemimpinanku pun kurang dan tidak jenaka.
HELLO, I'M SHIN SOL-I…
HALO, AKU SHIN SOL-I…
YOU CAN DO IT!
SEMANGAT!
You've got this!
Semangat!
I easily make mistakes,
Aku sering membuat kesalahan
and I make lots of clumsy mistakes.
dan berbuat bodoh.
However, that's why
Namun, itu sebabnya,
We'll be spending the most important days of our lives together.
Ke depannya, kita akan menjalani saat terpenting dalam hidup bersama-sama.
When the year is over, rather than a clumsy troublemaker,
Setelah tahun ini, aku ingin diingat sebagai Shin Sol-i, ketua kelas
I'd like to be remembered
yang selalu membantu dan disukai
as your favorite class president who helped and spoke up for everyone.
oleh kalian semua, bukan Shin Sol-i yang sering berulah.
I'll do my best!
Aku akan berusaha maksimal.
Here.
Ini.
Thanks for helping me with my speech.
Terima kasih sudah bantu memeriksa naskah pidatoku.
No, thanks.
Tidak perlu.
Don't refuse. Just take them.
Terimalah.
Hui-ji made it for you. Why let them go to waste?
Hui-ji membuatnya sendiri. Sayang jika tak dimakan.
He accepted it!
Selamat!
Look, it's the vice president.
Ya ampun, ada Wakil Ketua Kelas.
She got lucky, if you ask me.
Wakil Ketua saja sudah bagus.
Talk about not knowing your place.
Mestinya kau tahu diri.
Stop it.
Jangan begitu.
What? Am I wrong?
Memang kenapa?
What about you?
Lantas kau siapa?
You should know your place.
Kau yang mestinya tahu diri.
It's all right.
Tidak apa.
Tell me why you didn't vote for Sol-i.
Katakan. Kenapa kau tak pilih Sol-i?
She's not it.
Tentu karena tak pantas.
TWO HOURS AGO
DUA JAM LALU
Hui-ji and Sol-i are at a tie.
Hui-ji dan Sol-i seri.
Heon,
Cha Heon!
who will you vote for?
Kau pilih siapa?
Heon, I'm right here.
Hei, Cha Heon! Aku di sini.
Don't forget I'm your partner.
Jangan lupa aku teman sebangkumu.
Oh Hui-ji.
Oh Hui-ji.
Hey, Cha Heon.
Hei, Cha Heon!
-What? -Why am I not up to the job?
- Kenapa? - Kenapa aku tak pantas?
You're not leader material.
Sebab begitulah adanya.
And Hui-ji is?
Sedangkan Hui-ji pantas?
Compared to you, yes.
Ya, jika dibanding kau.
Hey!
Hei!
You kicked him hard?
Keras-keras pula?
Keep it down, will you?
Bicara pelan-pelan.
Wow, Sol-i, I'm really impressed.
Shin Sol-i, aku terharu kepadamu.
You taught him a lesson.
Kau balas dendam sepatutnya.
Why am I exhilarated when you're the one who kicked him?
Kau yang menendang Cha Heon,
I don't know what to do right now.
tapi kenapa aku yang girang?
Do you think he'll accept my apology?
Apa dia akan memaafkanku?
Heon, wait up!
Cha Heon, tunggu!
No way. I just can't believe it.
Sungguh sulit dipercaya!
Sol-i kicked you?
Shin Sol-i menendang…
Sol-i, Shin Sol-i!
Shin So-i!
What?
Kenapa?
-Here you go. -What's this?
- Ini. - Apa ini?
Hui-ji told me to give it to you.
Kata Hui-ji, kau yang kumpulkan.
-Me? -That's all I know.
- Aku? - Entah.
She's making you do all the work now.
Dia ingin lepas tanggung jawab, ya?
Ha-young, what do I do?
Ha-young, aku harus bagaimana?
What else can you do?
Bagaimana apanya?
It's your job as the vice president.
Kau Wakil Ketua. Apa boleh buat?
No, I mean about Heon.
Bukan. Maksudku, Cha Heon.
How am I supposed to ask him to pay the money?
Bagaimana aku minta uang kaus kelas kepadanya?
What? Just ask.
Tinggal bilang saja.
Put him in a headlock and point a gun at him.
Rangkul pundaknya, arahkan pistol,
"Bang! Pay up."
lalu bilang, "Berikan uangnya!"
But he's too tall for me.
Aku pendek.
Do it when he's seated. He usually is, anyway.
Lakukan saat dia duduk. Dia selalu duduk seharian.
Okay, one, two, three. One!
Ayo mulai! Satu, dua, tiga. Satu!
-Darn it. -Hang in there.
- Ayo! - Lima!
You're caving in. Jeez.
Tidak boleh. Apa-apaan kau?
Do it!
Cepat maju!
"Bang! Pay up."
Arahkan pistol, lalu bilang, "Berikan uangnya!"
God, that was so cheap.
Kau menyebalkan.
How about another game?
Ayo, sekali lagi.
Hand me my change.
Kembalian.
Heon,
Heon.
Ms. Moon said I should ask you to recommend some English books,
Tadi Wali Kelas menyuruhku minta rekomendasi buku bahasa Inggris kepadamu.
since you've read a lot.
Katanya kau sudah baca banyak.
I want to start reading in English.
Aku baru ingin baca buku berbahasa Inggris,
What books do you recommend?
lebih baik baca buku apa?
-I'll write you a list later on. -Sure.
- Nanti aku beri daftarnya. - Baik.
Are you done collecting the money?
Uang kaus sudah dikumpulkan?
Ms. Moon wants it by this afternoon.
Ibu Guru minta dikumpulkan saat jam pulang.
Sure, got it.
Baiklah.
-Let's go. -Okay.
- Ayo! - Ya.
-What is it? -Where did it go?
- Ada apa? - Di mana, ya?
-Try to think. -Okay.
- Ingat baik-baik. - Ya.
Hand in your Korean language assignment.
Semua, kumpulkan PR bahasa Korea.
Here.
Punyaku juga.
SHIN SOL-I
SHIN SOL-I
This is crazy.
Aku bisa gila!
I think it's in my Korean language notebook.
Kurasa diselipkan di buku PR bahasa Korea.
Then get it back
Tinggal diambil.
before Hui-ji and Su-jin find out.
Kita ambil sebelum Hui-ji dan Su-jin tahu.
that means I'll have to go to the staff room
kita harus ke Ruang Guru, 'kan?
and the person who sits next to Mr. Kim…
Sedangkan meja di samping guru Bahasa Korea…
is Mr. Cho.
adalah Guru Penertib.
I won't be able to retrieve it.
Mustahil bisa mengambilnya.
KANG HA-YOUNG SHIN SOL-I
KANG HA-YOUNG SHIN SOL-I
Yes?
Ya?
What's wrong? Are you sick?
Kenapa? Kau sakit?
No.
Tidak.
Actually, my stomach hurts.
Aku sakit perut.
Really?
Sungguh?
Hi, Mr. Lee.
Selamat siang, Pak.
Mr. Lee, my stomach's killing me.
Pak, perutku sakit sekali.
Can I get medicine?
Bisa minta obat?
Where does it hurt?
Sakit sebelah mana?
Why don't you show me?
Biar kulihat.
Right.
Baik.
And this would be enteritis.
sedangkan ini flu perut.
Then…
Kalau begitu,
-Do they require different medicine? -Of course.
- obatnya berbeda? - Tentu.
The treatment varies depending on the illness.
Semua obat berbeda tergantung sumber sakitnya.
So…
Jadi…
And gender too.
Jenis kelamin pun penting.
Men and women need different medications.
Obat untuk pria dan wanita berbeda.
So be more specific.
Tepatnya apa?
consider me a girl.
aku minta obat untuk wanita.
Thank you!
Terima kasih.
What do I do?
Bagaimana ini?
Here.
Terima ini.
What?
Apa?
You lost the money, didn't you?
Uang kaus hilang, ya?
-No! -Is that so?
- Tidak. - Sungguh?
-Forget it, then. -Heon.
- Baiklah. - Heon!
Help me.
Tolong bantu aku.
-Why should I? -I'm sorry I kicked you.
- Untuk apa kubantu? - Maaf tadi aku menendangmu.
I was going to apologize right away. I mean it.
Aku sungguh berniat minta maaf segera.
If you help me,
Tolong aku!
I'll never forget your kindness.
Takkan kulupakan kebaikanmu selamanya.
Where did you lose it?
Hilang di mana?
I put it in the homework notebook I handed in.
Aku selipkan di buku PR bahasa Korea dan sudah diserahkan.
Then…
Kalau begitu…
why don't you go kick Mr. Kim in the shins, too?
tendang saja guru bahasa Korea.
I'm doomed!
Tidak! Matilah aku!
I'm sorry, but I'm begging you.
Maafkan aku. Aku mohon.
Please don't tell my classmates about this,
Tolong jangan beri tahu teman-teman sekelas.
especially Oh Hui-ji and Lee Su-jin.
Terutama, Oh Hui-ji dan Lee Su-jin
They can't find out about this.
jangan sampai tahu.
What are you doing?
Kau sedang apa?
Why are you blocking the door?
Kenapa menghalangi jalan?
STAFF ROOM
RUANG GURU
Heon, how are you feeling today?
Heon, apa kondisimu baik?
I envy him.
Sungguh iri.
Hui-ji, did you collect the money?
Hui-ji, uang kaus sudah dikumpulkan?
Yes, our vice president has it.
Ya, Wakil Ketua yang pegang.
Sol-i, what's wrong?
Ada apa, Sol-i?
I…
Aku…
CHA HEON
CHA HEON
Sol-i?
Sol-i?
Ms. Moon, I apologize.
Maafkan aku, Bu Guru.
I lost the money I'd collected,
Aku menghilangkan uang kaus kelas
and Heon's just recovered it for me.
dan Cha Heon baru saja menemukannya.
I knew she'd cause trouble.
Sudah kuduga.
I'm sorry, guys.
Maaf, Teman-teman.
I guess I shouldn't be the vice president.
Kurasa aku tak pantas jadi Wakil Ketua Kelas.
Shouldn't she resign?
Dia harus mengundurkan diri.
She messed up big time.
Itu kesalahan besar.
You think so?
Menurutmu?
Quiet, everyone.
Semua, tenang!
Anyone can make mistakes.
Siapa pun bisa berbuat salah.
Even I, your teacher, make mistakes.
Ibu pun begitu.
However, it's never easy to admit them.
Akan tetapi, mengakui kesalahan adalah hal yang sulit.
One has to be brave to openly admit their mistakes.
Ditambah butuh keberanian besar untuk bisa mengaku sendiri seperti ini.
That is why I believe
Jadi, menurut ibu,
It's not like the money's gone,
Uangnya tidak hilang.
so isn't it all right?
Kurasa itu tidak masalah.
-Right. Don't you agree? -The money's all there.
- Benar. Tidak apa. - Uangnya masih utuh.
That'll do.
Itu cukup.
Heon!
Heon.
Here you go.
Terima kasih.
Hey, what was that?
Hei, ada apa?
Nothing, sir.
Bukan apa-apa.
Get it together, all right?
Belajarlah yang rajin.
You guys are going to be seniors soon. Got it?
Kalian juga akan naik kelas tiga sebentar lagi. Paham?
Yes, sir.
Baik, Pak.
Let's go, Shin Sol-i!
Semangat, Shin Sol-i!
-Shin Sol-i! -Heon!
- Shin Sol-i! - Heon!
-The field day is next week-- -Which has nothing to do with you.
- Pekan depan ada Pesta Olahraga. - Apa urusannya denganmu?
Heon, do you know why she's practicing so hard?
Cha Heon, kau tahu kenapa dia berusaha begitu keras?
Mr. Lee, is Ha-young going to be all right?
Pak, Ha-young tidak apa, 'kan?
I have to go now.
Aku harus pergi.
-Is there any way? -Jump over the gate.
- Tak ada cara lain? - Bisa lewat pagar.
-What are you doing? -The dean's coming.
- Kalian sedang apa? - Ada Penertib.
-Don't be nervous. -Heon, will you help me?
- Tak perlu gugup. - Heon, kau mau membantuku?